<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-01T13:46:43-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Siva Sankar E.V.P</title><subtitle>A scratchpad containing my words on football, data science and other assorted topics.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Europe is Blue</title><link href="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/05/31/europe-is-blue.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Europe is Blue" /><published>2021-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-05-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/05/31/europe-is-blue</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/05/31/europe-is-blue.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;chelsea-fc---champions-of-europe-twice-over&quot;&gt;Chelsea F.C - Champions of Europe twice over&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea won the Champions League for the second time in their history on 28 May, 2021. Nine years and a bit after the first time they won it in a dramatic fashion. Before we get to the numbers, I want to reflect on my memories of this incredible football club’s tempestuous relationship with this competition, which was for so long the Holy Grail, the altar at which many managerial jobs were sacrificed. It seems that this sacrifice is a necessary appeasement to the gods to clear the path to victory and destiny.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;walk-down-the-memory-lane&quot;&gt;Walk down the memory lane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time Chelsea won the Champions League, I sat alone with my laptop in a dark room, heart thumping out of my chest for over 120 minutes. The entire ordeal was worth it because the players who were part of my earliest football memories and my sporting heroes, in their waning light pulled together and made a miracle happen. There was nothing else to it but a sheer desire to not give up and an overwhelming sense of destiny. It was an amazing experience I sadly had nobody around to share with and had to contain my excitement lest I wake my entire family up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t know when Chelsea would be back at this stage, we came close a couple of years down the line from that, but I will never forget that night. I forever will remember Ivanovic straddling the pole, Lampard running towards the fans, Drogba and Cech collapsing in tears of joy after finally slaying the beast that evaded them for the better part of a decade. Champions League nights are always special, even if you are half a world away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;glory-in-porto&quot;&gt;Glory in Porto&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9 years on from that day, I once again watched the match alone at home, this time a predicament imposed on me because the world outside my home is plague ridden. An insignificant inconvenience while so many suffer and lose their lives and their loved ones. I am eternally grateful that this virus has not touched the people I love and will continue to hope that it won’t. That said, to share this moment with people who share the same passion for my club would have meant the world. I will settle however for these few words shared with the internet, wanting only to convey my joy and share it with people who feel the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means everything that Mount and James, guys who I’ve followed closely from their U18 days have made their mark at the highest stage. It means everything that club legends Azpilicueta and N’Golo Kante can add the most elusive of trophies to their honors list. It means everything that a guy like Mendy can have a meteoric rise and have a complete amazing season in front of goal. These are just a few things that make this trophy special. If what happened in 2012 was the end of an era, then this is the beginning of a new one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-word-for-thomas-tuchel&quot;&gt;A word for Thomas Tuchel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a sense of detached calm I associate with Thomas Tuchel. There is also a sense of detachment with him as a coach. He is no doubt a passionate man who wants to win above all else. A very desirable trait in a manager. However, he acts with the knowledge and acceptance that one day he will be sacked, this frees him from playing the same politics and ego struggles that got many of his predecessors fired. Long may that continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His complete transformation of the flamboyant if flawed young team under Lampard to a defensive juggernaut is miraculous. A complete and utter sense of control has been at the root of all he has accomplished at Chelsea. A defense that is strong not because it can repel attackers and absorb pressure but because it simply doesn’t allow dangerous situations against itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cl_final/che_shot_against_distance_vs_outcome_lampard_vs_tuchel.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that, Tuchel added a tactical flair which allowed him to dominate all of his opponents on the way glory in the Champions League, won in a very convincing fashion against the media’s champions-elect Manchester City and Pep Guardiola. I never thought I’d see the day when Chelsea would need no miracles, no luck to win the Champions League. Every team needs a good serving of that to win it but Tuchel did without. A remarkable achievement less than 5 months into the job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;jekyll-twitter-plugin&quot;&gt;&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Chelsea&amp;#39;s dominance in the knockouts.... damn &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/ysjLwFpZtK&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/ysjLwFpZtK&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Michael Caley (@MC_of_A) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MC_of_A/status/1398762707373985798?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 29, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to what he will do next with excitement, knowing full well that he may be fired come next January. I guess that’s what being a grown up is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;evolution-after-a-revolution&quot;&gt;Evolution after a revolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two years ago, if you had told me that Mason Mount and Reece James would play starring roles in a season where Chelsea win the Champions League, I would not have believed you. There simply was no precedent. But desperate times call for desperate measures. Chelsea were losing their talisman, a man who singlehandedly got them top 4 and a European trophy before bowing out, in Eden Hazard. They were facing a transfer ban, so they did something radical. They hired an inexperienced coach in Lampard to come in and change the squad profile and boy did he deliver on that. Chelsea have found out that the academy boys are good enough and then some. I hope that this lesson won’t be forgotten. By all means, keep spending money on the Havertzses and Werners of the world but also allow the precocious talents carefully nurtured at Cobham to lay down their claim to the first team. If nothing else, by enhancing their value to other teams, Chelsea can continue to spend money by selling their very talented academy players at a markup. This evolution is needed after the revolution that happened in the previous season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;back-to-brass-tacks&quot;&gt;Back to brass tacks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea surprised City with their game plan. A lot was made of Pep not playing his hatchet men in midfield. Perhaps that was because he expected Chelsea to press them high and hence wanted Gundogan’s security and invention on the ball. Or perhaps, he knew that Chelsea roasted both Fernandinho and Rodri in previous games with ease, so he YOLOed his lineup to play to his beliefs. Chelsea however, had other plans. They allowed the City CBs to advance with little to no pressure on them. Majority of the effort was spent cutting out all passing options into the middle of the pitch, then asking the wingbacks to be touch tight and dominate the opposition wide players. This is clearly evident in the below pressure map of Chelsea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cl_final/MCICHE_cl_Chelsea_pressure_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting that James was Chelsea’s lowest positioned when it comes to applying defensive pressures, this tracks well with Sterling being City’s highest positioned player in possession. It would be an understatement to say that James dominated his area. With 5 tackles, 3 interceptions, 24 pressures and a pressure regain percentage of 45.8.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then there was N’Golo Kante, the bane of KdB’s existence on the night. He put in 22 pressures with a whopping 54.5% pressure regain percentage. He had 7 tackles+interceptions, 3 clearances and 2 blocked passes. He allowed nobody to dribble past him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cl_final/MCICHE_cl_Manchester_City_pressure_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the ball Kante was calm and collected. He executed a team high 11 passes under pressure, dribbled past his opponents twice in three attempts and  successfully received 30/32 passes targeted towards him. Given City’s high pressing and Chelsea’s tactic of absorbing pressure on the right, this was very impressive and a key part of our success. Give him the Ballon d’Or now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cl_final/MCICHE_cl_Manchester_City_touch_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;City CBs were unimpeded when trying to progress the ball and were aggressively positioned as usual. Gundogan’s role as a playmaker suffered from being denied the passing options into the block due to excellent work from the team to cut off passing lanes, forcing them wide into Sterling or Mahrez. Both wingers were turned into complete non-entities by James and Chilwell. All this ended up meaning that City were toothless in attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cl_final/MCICHE_cl_Chelsea_touch_map.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea on the other hand were clever with their approach to take the game to City. They absorbed pressure on the right and then switched to Mount and Chilwell who found themselves overloading City on that flank. Once the ball got to them, their responsibility was to advance it at pace. The same move occurred multiple times and ultimately paid dividends for the goal. Mount completed 92% of his passes. 6/25 were progressive passes and he executed 2/3 dribbles. As a player tasked with primary creative responsibility as well as ball progression, he is maturing every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody on the pitch had anything less than a perfect game but a special mention should go to Kai Havertz. He played his role to perfection. He ran at City well, completed 3/4 dribbles and won 4 fouls high up the pitch, especially late in the game. He also won 4/10 headers providing an aerial outlet on the right hand side of the pitch. A consummate center forward performance in the Champions League final. I believe there is more to come from him and that his best role is as part of a front 2. I hope that this finally kickstarts his Chelsea career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea beat City and Pep Guardiola thrice in one month, thoroughly. Tuchel and the team deserve immense credit for this. They showed up when it mattered, like the best Chelsea teams of past and delivered on the biggest occasion. The world is at this Chelsea squad’s feet now and sky is the limit to what they can achieve. Nearly 18 years after the first magnificent Chelsea team under Roman, we have the makings of the second one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data was taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fbref.com/en/&quot;&gt;Fbref.com&lt;/a&gt; courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://statsbomb.com/&quot;&gt;Statsbomb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SB_Regular.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Statsbomb's logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Chelsea F.C - Champions of Europe twice over</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dipping into Usage rates</title><link href="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/03/20/dipping-into-usage-rates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dipping into Usage rates" /><published>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-03-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/03/20/dipping-into-usage-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2021/03/20/dipping-into-usage-rates.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;defining-possession-usage-rates&quot;&gt;Defining Possession Usage rates&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-calculations&quot;&gt;The calculations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usage rate is a metric used in basketball analytics to understand how much of a team’s possessions are used by a player. This metric has been shown to be correlated with centrality in pass network by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mlssoccer.com/post/2014/08/20/central-winger-how-measure-players-influence-through-touches-or-lack-thereof&quot;&gt;Devin Pleuler&lt;/a&gt;. It allows us to measure which players on a team are central to the attack and how efficient they are with the ball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbastuffer.com/analytics101/usage-rate/&quot;&gt;Usage rate&lt;/a&gt;, a.k.a., usage percentage is an estimate of the percentage of team plays used by a player while he was on the floor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have used &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onceinabluemean.com/2015/11/city-is-kevin-de-bruynes-team-already.html&quot;&gt;Martin Hawkes-Teeter&lt;/a&gt;’s definitions of Usage rates and positive to negative ratios in this article. The formula is rather straightforward as can be seen below. Terms which have a ‘+’ sign as a superscript are considered positive actions and those with a ‘-‘ sign are considered negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://latex.codecogs.com/gif.download?%5Clarge%20%5CLarge%20Usage%20Rate%20%3D%20%5Cfrac%7B%28Shots%5E+%20+%20KeyPasses%5E+%20+%20Miscontrols%5E-%20+%20Dispossessions%5E-%20+%20Unsuccesful%20Take%20Ons%5E-%20+%20Unsuccesful%20Passes%5E-%29%7D%7B%28SquadTotals%20*%20%5Cfrac%7B90s%5C%20Played%7D%7BTotal%5C%2090s%7D%29%7D&quot; alt=&quot;\Large UsageRate=\frac{(Shots^+ + KeyPasses^+ + Miscontrols^- + Dispossessions^- + Unsuccesful Take Ons^- + Unsuccesful Passes^-)}{(SquadTotals * \frac{90s\ Played}{Total\ 90s})}&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the context set, let’s dive into the profiles of some teams in the Premier League over the last 4 seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chelsea&quot;&gt;Chelsea&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-hazard-era&quot;&gt;The Hazard era&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chelsea’s attack was often described as completely dependent on Eden Hazard during his time here. This is particularly true under Sarri’s regime. Him and Willian are on a completely different level in terms of using possession and also being highly efficient with their actions. The median usage rate is the lowest it has been while the efficiency is pretty high. That goes to show that the majority of attaking impetus and risk taking came from Hazard and to an extent Willian. This is also borne out by the fact that Hazard had the most positive actions(183 Shots+KP). Only Willian is remotely close to him with 144. Everybody else is well below 100. This disparity shows up stronger when looking at overall numbers. Hazard used 829 possessions, the closest player to him is Willian with 576. One man show.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/LSJneAx.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;post-hazard-era&quot;&gt;Post-Hazard era&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hakim Ziyech has always been a high usage player. That has usually been coupled with excellent output. If he doesn’t provide that, he’s a liability to the team. Mason Mount has taken a huge leap forward over last season. Reece is having a really good season too. Influential in attack coupled with good efficiency while improving his defensive skills with every passing game. Chilwell is an interesting case for a fullback. He’s a very attacking player who puts up some good ball progression and crossing numbers. If he can improve his efficiency, he can make a case for being the best attacking fullback in the league. Kai Havertz while not contributing much has been tidy, Pulisic on the other hand has had a huge fall from last season. His efficiency has dropped to 20% from 30% last season. Need improvements there. Callum on the other hand, very efficient on the ball and has excellent efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;manchester-city&quot;&gt;Manchester City&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kevin de Bruyne is amazing. When he’s fit and firing, there’s simply nobody in the PL who can touch him in terms of creativity. He is the hub of this team Pep has built. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/qK6p8ee.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;liverpool&quot;&gt;Liverpool&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All I can say is Salah, Mane and Firmino are exceptionally efficient players. Trent had a monster season in 2019-20. Sole creative hub of a team, supported only by Robertson. The midfield and defense not really contributing much that season in terms of attacking risk-taking. That passes the eye test.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/EsrmPTO.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;manchester-united&quot;&gt;Manchester United&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the Bruno Fernandes show at Manchester United. He has a very high influence on United’s attack but he’s also wasteful. Nobody else really takes risks, so that works out well for them. Luke Shaw is also having a really good season.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/KEuEClH.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;leicester-city&quot;&gt;Leicester City&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvey Barnes and James Maddison are really good. Tielemans is very interesting for a player who has played deeper and deeper with every passing season. Has a higher usage rate than most midfielders and had an excellent efficiency last season. 
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/9YzgXIg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-summation&quot;&gt;In summation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good way to measure who is influencing a team’s attack. The obvious candidates(de Bruyne, Fernandes) standout starkly. There seems to be clear correlation between player position and their usage rates. The players who show up radically different to where they’re expected to be, TAA, Robertson and Chilwell in fullback positions for example, do so for the right reasons. I plan on expanding this analysis by performing a cluster analysis and seeing how well that can predict a player’s position. Usage rates can also be applied to other statistics such as pressures, progressive carries/passes etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data was taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fbref.com/en/&quot;&gt;Fbref.com&lt;/a&gt; courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://statsbomb.com/&quot;&gt;Statsbomb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SB_Regular.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Statsbomb's logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Defining Possession Usage rates</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digging into shots</title><link href="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2020/08/06/digging-into-shots.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digging into shots" /><published>2020-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-08-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2020/08/06/digging-into-shots</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://blog.eternalblue.co.in/football/2020/08/06/digging-into-shots.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;historical-study-of-chelseas-shots&quot;&gt;Historical study of Chelsea’s shots&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;premise&quot;&gt;Premise&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has been nearly a year since Frank Lampard has taken charge of Chelsea F.C. There has been a lot of debate about how to judge his first season. Chelsea achieved their goal of finishing in the top 4 and have also reached a cup final. The fans were treated to sparkling attacking play at times. However, this was coupled with a tendency to concede goals at unfortunate times in games. Keeping that in mind, I decided to take a look at how far away the team were taking their shots from and the outcomes of these shots. To put things in a historical context, I also compared the data from the 2019-20 season to the past two seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-impressions&quot;&gt;First Impressions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are definite improvements in where we shoot from and how often. The number of shots we concede has gone down as well. Normally this would be cause for celebration. However, Chelsea have also conceded a lot of goals. This stat has also been an easy stick with which to beat Frank Lampard. The rest of the analysis will take a closer look at both shots taken and shots conceded in order to see if there may be some mitigating circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Overall Shot Rates
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/l9ZXMhy.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Takeaway: Shots taken per 90 have gone up. Shots conceded per 90 have gone down.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shot Rates by Distance to Goal
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/nSuI0VW.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Takeaway: More shots are being taken within the 10 yard range. Fewer shots were conceded overall and also closer to goal&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shot Rates by Outcome
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/1MSPfwp.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Takeaway: The goals conceded stat bucks the general trend of decrease in shots conceded&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;big-gains-in-attack&quot;&gt;Big gains in attack&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chelsea have improved quite a bit in attack as compared to the past couple of seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shots Taken by Outcome and Distance to goal
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/YtBHM4b.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a quick glance, the number of shots Chelsea take closer to goal has increased. There are big jumps in the numbers of saved, blocked and off target shots in the ten-yard range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that this hasn’t translated to more goals scored from that range tells me that Chelsea have been unlucky at times but also, their finishing quality needs to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s significant is just how much of an improvement this is from the last two seasons. The number of shots which are off target or blocked in the 10 yard range need to translate into more goals than Chelsea have scored, even though the current tally is still an improvement over previous seasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Change in Shots Taken
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/zBf96XY.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, Chelsea have added Timo Werner, an experienced striker who has scored 28 goals in league play. On the chance creation front, they have also added a world-class left footed wide creator in Ziyech and the creative potential of Reece James remains untapped. Things have been good on this front and will potentially get much better with added quality in attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;defensive-doldrums&quot;&gt;Defensive Doldrums&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-incongruities&quot;&gt;The incongruities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that Chelsea have conceded so many more goals than the previous seasons is a big problem and a question mark on Lampard’s ability to fix this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat, there are some mitigating circumstances. The front 5 of the team has skewed quite young. Youthful exuberance/inexperience has meant that controlling games has been a challenge. Kanté has been available only 50 per cent of the time this season and has spent a significant amount of that time finding fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equally, I don’t want to downplay just how much of a disaster each member of Chelsea’s backline has been at various times this season. This has meant that Lampard couldn’t settle on a first-choice defensive partnership. It has also meant that Lampard has been forced to drop the most expensive goalkeeper on the planet multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a case to be made that we were lucky not to have conceded more last season as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Shots Conceded by Outcome and Distance to goal
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/S1Xpl4a.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Takeaway: The number of shots off target in the 10-yard zone 2018-19 season is well above the other two seasons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Change in Shots conceded
&lt;img src=&quot;https://i.imgur.com/qTDOKso.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
Takeaway: Shot concession in the 10-yard zone has remained on par with last season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;possible-explanations&quot;&gt;Possible explanations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chelsea have consistently defended higher up the pitch than under Conte in 2017-18, who set up to defend deep and allow shots from range. His teams were very good at not allowing players to take shots closer to goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chelsea have also consistently conceded more goals from range since the departure of Courtois. Chelsea concede fewer shots from range, but the drop in the number of saves Kepa makes from range, coupled with the increase in goals conceded from this range is somewhat telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding poor goalkeeping, the number of goals Chelsea have conceded is still shocking. A lot more shots went off target last season as compared to this season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One explanation for this could be that Chelsea were very good at pressuring shot takers inside the box last season. The strength of this argument however is undercut by the fact that the only missing piece from last season’s defense is David Luiz, hardly a paragon for being alive in the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of it can also be explained by the opposition just having their shooting boots on when we have faced them this season, and maybe not so much last season. An argument ever so slightly strengthened by the fact that quite a few players have broken their goalscoring ducks against Chelsea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defense dropping deeper to account for Kepa’s lack of range in moving off the line could also be one factor. There is clearly no trust in the goalkeeper both from the coach and the outfield players.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solutions&quot;&gt;Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, the fact that Chelsea tend to be asleep when shots are being taken in close range is something that needs to be fixed immediately. That means putting better defensive pressure and having better setups when defending set pieces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that a stronger and more cynical attitude needs to be taken in duels with strikers in wide areas around the halfway line. Losing the battle in these areas means conceding a dangerous counter-attack with most of our players stuck chasing play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of those issues however, can be fixed with a mix of new personnel and better coaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-summation&quot;&gt;In summation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I look forward to Lampard expanding his coaching team, and bringing in people who have different perspectives to what is a homogeneous staff, full of people who learned how to coach at Chelsea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also look forward to Chelsea having a fully fit Kanté, a DM who fits Lampard’s needs and center backs and left backs who are suited to a back-4 and the Premier League.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are looking really good in attack. On the surface, things look good in defense too. Chelsea just need to get to get the intangibles of defending right, like leadership, personal responsibility and toughness. There is every reason for Chelsea fans to be excited for next season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;credits&quot;&gt;Credits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article was originally posted on the excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://weaintgotnohistory.sbnation.com/2020/8/6/21356985/digging-into-shots&quot;&gt;We Ain’t Got No History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data was taken from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fbref.com/en/&quot;&gt;Fbref.com&lt;/a&gt; courtesy of &lt;a href=&quot;https://statsbomb.com/&quot;&gt;Statsbomb&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/SB_Regular.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;Statsbomb's logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="football" /><summary type="html">Historical study of Chelsea’s shots</summary></entry></feed>